let's talk about the lumbo-pelvic HIPAA
complex biomechanics with glute
exercises so here I've got a spine and
pelvis model and I want to teach you why
we coach various exercise the way we do
here at glute lab so first let's discuss
lumbo-pelvic rhythm so the pelvis and
hips and lumbar spine have sort of a
rhythm to them the pelvis can rotate
forward and backward and when it does
the spine tends to go with it a little
bit so when you anteriorly tilt the
pelvis like I do here you get some
lumbar extension when you post early
pelvic tilt the pelvis you get some
lumbar flexion so there's lumbar motion
associated with a pelvic motion now Mel
sif first pointed this out in his book
super training but he mentioned that
when you're at the bottom of a lift like
a squat or a deadlift you want a little
bit of anterior pelvic tilt the reason
why you want this is because as you pull
from the ground the load is trying to
pull you into flexion so just the
attempt to create a little bit of
anterior tilt is gonna protect you from
going into those dangerous levels of
lumbar flexion now I also mentioned that
during exercises like loaded carries or
sit ups you want slight post your pelvic
tilt simply because it's trying to pull
you into lumbar extension and that'll
buttress you against going into that now
how does the spine get damaged
there are many mechanisms for back
related injuries and pain but during
lumbar flexion you will have the
erectors and the ab muscles basically
any muscle that attaches from the
ribcage to the pelvis and when these
muscles contract like the erectors
abdominals in the front obliques you're
gonna have compressive forces so picture
a rib cage here and picture muscles kind
of clamping down this creates
compressive forces which pushes down
most people mistakenly assume that
having a bar on your back or on a bar on
your hands creates a ton of compressive
force in here when not only
it's a small percentage the majority the
percentage comes from the muscles
themselves counteracting those loads and
really clamping down on the spine so
when the spine doesn't have compressive
forces and it moves around in flexion
and extension it's not as dangerous
unloaded movements don't tend to cause
injuries it's when you have the
compressive forces and then you flex and
extend that's when it's increasingly
more dangerous and you'll even see here
on this model they've got a herniation
because when you have compression and
then you flex significantly what happens
at the disk level you can see here if I
push this way you can envision this
pinches together and then it pushes the
nucleus rearward and you end up with a
posterolateral disk herniation as you
see here so how does this apply to
squats and deadlifts and hip thrusts and
back extensions
[Music]
during squats and deadlifts you're gonna
have compressive forces there's no way
around it because as you bend over to
pick up the weight in a deadlift
or as you squat down you lean forward if
you erectors weren't activated you would
round over completely so they have to be
activated in order to use good form and
that erector activation creates that
compressive force so you're gonna have
high compressive forces and so when you
have compressive forces you want to make
sure you remain mostly neutral
well again the studies that measure
lumbar spine movement during heavy
resistance exercise show that even when
you're trying to remain in neutral you
always end up flexing a little bit
usually around 26 degrees so that intent
to create lumbar extension and anterior
pelvic tilt as you pull the weight off
the ground helps safeguard you from
going into flexion but you want to
minimize the amount of motion here under
the high compressive forces during
squats and deadlifts and that's why I
recommend slide into your pelvic tilt at
the bottom now if you go deep in a squat
and you have poor hip flexion mobility
your femur will actually collide here
and pull you and a butt wink or post
your pelvic tilt in a squat in a
deadlift if you have poor hamstring
flexibility you'll bend over and you'll
just end up rounding because your
hamstrings run out so in that case you
can't hold it into your pelvic tilt
while going deep so make sure that you
go don't go too deep for your anatomical
limitations now let's talk about the hip
thrust
so a lot of coaches in a hip thrusts say
that you should try to stay neutral okay
this would be staying neutral but I
believe that as you rise up you should
actually post your pelvic tilt like this
and the reason why is because if you
stay in neutral you always end up
arching a little bit you end up going
into some extension like this and this
is confirmed by EMG which shows that
you're getting a similar amount of
erector activity during hip thrusts as
deadlifts when you stay in neutral so
you're getting high compressive forces
with that extension which is problematic
when you have high compressive forces
and extension you're more likely to
damage these posts or elements of the
spine like the facet joints for example
so you're more likely to cause injury in
pain when you have high compressive
forces and extension however when you
post your pelvic tilt you're using the
glutes to help extend the hips because
post your pelvic tilt is very similar to
hip extension in the sense that in your
acetabulum doing this versus doing this
is similar you wouldn't know the
difference in the acetabulum so post
your pelvic tilt mimics hip
hyperextension so basically you're using
the glutes to take you from here to here
and you're minimizing the erector
activation so when you reduce erector
activation you reduce the compressive
forces and use the glutes to extend the
hip you're using glutes to post your
pelvic tilt not abdominals if you try to
do a crunch actively and use the
abdominals to post your pelvic tilt then
you'd create those compressive forces
but the glutes don't create compressive
forces at the spine so here you have
markedly reduced compressive forces also
you're gonna have reduced shear forces
and so this ends up being a much safer
lift okay yes you might go into a little
bit of
collection here but it's unloaded so to
reiterate here you are at the bottom of
a hip thrust all right this would be
staying in neutral when people try to do
this as they rep to failure or as they
go a little too heavy they always end up
and tear tilting like this and extending
the lumbar spine and this is when pain
occurs this is when you get damage to
the posterior of the spine so to
safeguard against this I recommend post
your pelvic tilting so you end up at the
top like this and this way you minimize
the compressive forces so the spinal
motion associated with this a little bit
of flexion doesn't incur any damage and
you use mostly glutes and it's more of a
pure hip extensor exercise because
you're using glutes and hamstrings and
minimizing erector activity and this
makes it safer over the long run so as
you can see spinal biomechanics is a
complicated topic and you can't just
assume that you should use the same
exact spinal and pelvic posture no
matter what the exercise because it
depends whether the load is axial as in
the case of a squat or a deadlift and it
comes vertical relative to the body
versus horizontal as is the case of hip
thrusts or even back extensions where
you're coming up like that in this case
you'd use a different lumbo-pelvic hip
complex strategy depending on whether
the load is horizontal versus vertical
or anteroposterior versus axial thanks
for watching